<resources>
    <string name="app_name" translatable="false">Madrid Encantada</string>
    <string name="title_activity_main" translatable="false">MainActivity</string>
    <string name="map">Map</string>
    <string name="points_of_interest">Points of interest</string>
    <string name="options">Options</string>
    <string name="audio_guide">Audio Guide</string>
    <string name="language_key_preferencias" translatable="false">Idioma</string>  <!--  NO TRADUCIR -->
    <string name="manual">Manual</string>
    <string name="title_activity_map" translatable="false">MapActivity</string>
    <string name="title_activity_point_map">Map</string>
    <string name="title_activity_all_points_of_interest">All points of interest</string>
    <string name="title_activity_audio_maps">Audio guide</string>
    <string name="welcome" translatable="false">MADRID ENCANTADA</string>
    <string name="welcome2">A ghostly app</string>


    <!--Puntos de interés-->
    <string name="sofia">Reina Sofia Museum</string>
    <string name="banco">Bank of Spain</string>
    <string name="ayuntamiento">Communicactions Palace (Cityhall of Madrid)</string>
    <string name="linares">Linares\' Palace (American\'s house)</string>
    <string name="ejercito">Headquarters of the Army</string>
    <string name="chimenea">The house of the 7 chimneys</string>
    <string name="iglesia">San Jose´s church</string>
    <string name="teatro">Español theater</string>
    <string name="ana">Santa Ana´s square</string>
    <string name="hotel">Hotel del Gato</string>
    <string name="cabeza">Cabeza Street</string>
    <string name="palacio">Santa Cruz\' Palace</string>
    <string name="mayor">Main square (Plaza Mayor)</string>
    <!-- FIN puntos de interés-->

    <string name="guide_me">Bring me there</string>
    <string name="ipsum" translatable="false">Lorem fistrum sexuarl torpedo no puedor por la gloria de mi madre apetecan qué dise usteer ese pedazo de. A wan va usté muy cargadoo te va a hasé pupitaa apetecan pupita quietooor al ataquerl no puedor. Está la cosa muy malar qué dise usteer a gramenawer a peich. Qué dise usteer me cago en tus muelas a wan se calle ustée ese hombree mamaar a peich. Torpedo amatomaa torpedo me cago en tus muelas ese pedazo de no te digo trigo por no llamarte Rodrigor al ataquerl mamaar apetecan a gramenawer no te digo trigo por no llamarte Rodrigor. </string>
    <string name="how_to_arrive">How to arrive</string>
    <string name="listen">Audio</string>
    <string name="key_language" translatable="false">language</string>
    <string name="surf">Select any points</string>
    <string name="explain_audio">The audio will be played when you get close to the point</string>
    <string name="history">History</string>
    <string name="information">Information</string>

    <!--GPS-->
    <string name="gps_network_not_enabled">GPS is not activated</string>
    <string name="open_location_settings">Open GPS options</string>
    <string name="Cancel">Cancel</string>
    <string name="gps_permitions">Accept geolocation permissions</string>
    <string name="gps_near">You are close to</string>
    <string name="gps_inside">YOU ARE IN</string>
    <string name="toast_gps">Please allow GPS connection</string>

    <!--IDIOMAS-->
    <string name="str_button">Change languaje</string>
    <string name="str_spanish">Spanish</string>
    <string name="str_english">English</string>
    <string-array name="languages">
        <item>@string/str_spanish</item>
        <item>@string/str_english</item>
    </string-array>
    <string name="english">English</string>
    <string name="spanish">Spanish</string>
    <string name="language">Language</string>

    <!-- TEXTOS -->
    <string name="historia_ejercito">At the end of the eighteenth century (1777), the Dukes of Alba ordered to build on this estate what was to be called the Buenavista Palace. Richly decorated with paintings and sculptures, the palace has always been accompanied by tragedy. Thus after two fires, the building was expropriated to the dukes in 1807 and Fernando VII quickly made it available to the military. Since then, great personalities of the History of Spain (generals Espartero and Prim, Manuel Azaña, Miguel Primo de Rivera ...) have lodged between their walls with unequal fortune.\n\n
        The first of the stories surrounding this building speaks of a Civil Guard who would have killed himself near the Stairs of Honor. Since then lot of soldiers say they have heard steps without owner, felt sudden changes of temperature and they even speak of an armored door that has opened without anyone triggering its mechanism.\n\n
        We talked before the stay of personalities in the palace. For General Prim this would be his last dwelling since on December 30, 1870 this military man would die in strange circumstances and even today one can perceive in his quarters an inquisitive presence that seems to want to urge us to discover the truth about his death.</string>

    <string name="historia_museo">If we have learned anything from the horror films of the last few decades, it is that building something, whatever it is, inside the enclosure of what used to be a hospital is not the best of the ideas. One of the most important art galleries in the capital, was born as San Carlos hospital back in the time of Felipe III. The building, always surrounded by the mists of mystery and on which dozens of rumors about ghosts and specters in its windows ran, saw its history growing and reaching all corners of Spain after the decision to lodge the Guernica on its walls , Perhaps the most famous painting of the genius Pablo Picasso.\n\n
        The events around this building have been so many and so intense (elevators that worked alone without electric current, appearances in dark corridors ...) that motivated a series of complaints against the City of Madrid in 2000 by a cleaner who was terrified by the inexplicable events that he had witnessed there.</string>
    <string name="information_museo">For more information about prices and timetables please visit its official web page</string>

    <string name="historia_banco">What does a nun do in the cellars of the main financial institution in our country? No, it\'s not a bad joke. But the appearance of a spectrum dressed in a white habit that has been dedicated to complicate the life of the cleaning staff of the emblematic building to the point that there is real fear on the part of employees to go through according to which corridors without company.\n\n
        To find an explanation we have to go back to 1891, the year in which the first version of the building is inaugurated (previous to later expansions). For its construction there were demolished the palace of the marquesses of Alcañices and the church of San Fermin of the Navarros. Was there perhaps a nun buried there who did not see well that her eternal rest was disturbed by the works of a temple dedicated to the vile metal? We cannot find out because of the secrecy that surrounds everything that happens behind the walls of this building, but it is curious that the corridors where more appearances have been reported correspond to those that lead to the rooms where the documents that tell the story of the Bank are kept and that more than one worker has talked about books whose pages are spent alone in these sections of the building.</string>
    <string name="information_banco">You can pay a virtual visit through Bank of Spain web page</string>

    <string name="historia_ayuntamiento">Within our journey through the dark and the hidden of the Haunted Villa of Madrid we could not let the headquarters of his government pass. The former Post Office (or Post Office Palace), built at the beginning of the 20th century and silent witness to the bloodiest episodes of the Civil War, was falling into disuse within the years and the gradual entry of new technologies. Until 2007 it was decided to give a new life to the building by turning it into the new and brand new headquarters of the City of Madrid.\n\n
        The work to refurbish the old palace was progressing, when Manuel Ramirez Torrecilla (a relatively young ex-guard of the precinct), on a fateful January afternoon, parked his car in front of the doors to the Calle Montalbán, entered the palace and greeted the actual guard with six shots of the shotgun in his hands. Without trembling his pulse, Manuel reloaded and continued advancing to end the life of another of the vigilantes and seriously wounding a third (also with six shots) while a fourth security officer and a worker watched the scene terrorized from a safe place. From there they would see Manuel standing in the middle of the yard, looking around as if he had just awakened from a dream and aimed himself with the murder weapon to end up committing suicide.\n\n
        This makes us realize that it is not necessary to go much back to find stories of ghosts and apparitions. And is that, as a result of these facts, every time that an anniversary of the massacre of the city council is approaching there are those who say that you can hear steps that advance from the doors of the street Montalbán. Steps that stop only when they are drowned by the echoes of a shotgun that shoots again and again.</string>

    <string name="historia_america">Probably the most famous of all the enchanted places of the capital and central place of one of its most tragic stories. In the middle of Cibeles square, in 1873, Don José de Murga built a mansion that was to become, in addition to his residence, a place of meetings and parties for the upper class in Madrid. Too bad that by the time the building could be completely inaugurated (in 1900) the Marquis de Linares had already been dead for two years.\n\n
        The story goes that Don Francisco Mateo de Murga, father of our protagonist, was known for his encouragement to the party and his many love affairs away from the marital bed. One of these amorous dribbling would result in the birth of a girl (Raimunda) of whom, over the years, Don José would fall madly in love. José\'s father, aware of the blood ties that united the two lovers, would have strongly opposed this relationship. But when his father died, Don José found no obstacle to marry this humble tent.\n\n
        Here the stories are mixed and somewhat confusing. And although there are those who say that both lovers knew from Don Francisco\'s about their status as half-brothers, other stories tell us about a happy couple who, shortly after having their first daughter, would have discovered (thanks to some old letters of his father) belonging to the same lineage and who, fearful of repercussions, would have ended the life of the newborn baby. The other version, equally truculent, speaks of a clergy who reluctantly approved of their union on the condition that they did not leave offspring and a couple who, faced with the prospect of losing their social status, would have opted to end the life of their daughter.\n\n
        Since then, hundreds of sightings of figures who wander about in the windows of the palace have been reported. There are also numerous psychophonies of laughter, baby cries and even phrases that takes the wind (it is famous that one of \"Take my skirt away\") that have been documented in this place.</string>

    <string name="historia_chimeneas">We are faced with one of the oldest (and most haunted) houses of the Villa de Madrid.\n\n
        In this building lived Captain Zapata and his wife Elena, who was said to be a lover of King Felipe II, a rumor that only grew after the Zapata march to the long war that was being fought in Flandes, and in which he would end up losing his life. The truth is that Ms. Elena did not enjoy for a long time his status as a widow since, shortly after her husband died, the young woman appeared dead in her bedroom and, before it gave time to bury her, his body disappeared without leaving trail. Since then many voices claim to have seen a young maiden walk among the seven chimneys that give the building its name.\n\n
        The house was not empty for long, and soon a wealthy old man and his young wife (also lover of the same king according to the gossips) would coexist under his roof. But this lady would also be found dead (by suicide), her ghost going to roam the basement of the building, where at the end of the nineteenth century the remains of a woman would be found. \n\n
        But this does not end here. With the roofs and the basement taken by the ghostly beings we have the rest of the house. And to occupy it, what better than the butler of Esquilache? That\'s right, the person responsible for one of the capital\'s bloodiest riots stayed in this house in the time of Charles III, and when the tumult took place and the angry crowd went to his house, only his faithful butler avoided (at the cost of his own life) that the mob took control of the building. There is no shortage of witnesses who claim to have seen a figure dressed like a man of that century going through the corridors of the house of the 7 chimneys. </string>
    <string name="information_chimeneas" translatable="false">Plaza del Rey, 1</string>
    
    <string name="historia_iglesia">On which was the house of Lope de Vega, it was built in 1773 this magnificent church that, in the middle of the nineteenth century, would witness a mysterious event.\n\n
        It happened during Carnival celebrations (last moment of madness before the serious Lent) when a young Englishman fell madly in love with a girl (named Elena) whom he met at one of the many celebrations that were held in the capital. The two young people would spend the night together and, at the end of it, she would have asked him to accompany him back home. It would be in front of this church when the young woman suddenly said to her, \"I must go, my love. We will never see each other again, \'cause tomorrow is my funeral.\" After which, the girl fled from the embrace of her beloved to the then dark recesses of the sacred building.\n\n
        Astonished, our young man would return the next day to San Jose to try to meet again Elena, only to find the church crowded by the mass in honor of the recently dead Elena de Mendoza, who rested, with a body present in the center and in front of the altar. Surprised to see a noble foreigner, a cousin of the deceased would approach our boy, who would tell her about their encounter the previous day for the Carnival festivities. She told him that it was impossible that her cousin had gone to any party since she found the death at eight p.m. to which the young man would respond: I met her at that hour.</string>

    <string name="historia_teatro">Some will say that artists, because of their special sensitivity, are more likely to see things where they are not. But even if this is so, it is curious the enormous accumulation of paranormal events that take place in one of the oldest theaters in Spain. El Español, which looks majestically at the Plaza de Santa Ana, has been the scene of wonderful nights of theater... followed by dark dawns of unexplained events.\n\n
        Perhaps it would be well to keep in mind that in the basement you can still find the crypt of an old convent of the nuns of Santa Ana, felled during the Desamortización of 1836. Or you would have to dig into its history of fires (three with the same poit of origin, behind the scenes) and suicides to understand the reason of so many  legends of footsteps, presences, appearances and even attacks on theater workers that have led, on some occasion, to cause more than a serious attack of panic and anxiety.\n\n
        We do not have to go very far in History to find stories of apparitions. In the 90\'s of the last century, for example, it was customary to perform from time to time the work of Don Juan Tenorio, and there are a few actors and shipbuilders who claim to have seen the figure of a man dressed in vintage stroll walking through the empty hallways of the theater while in the scene it was being plaid the function of that day. It is also famous the case of the cleaner who, when approaching the bust of Tirso de Molina that governs one of its corridors, felt a warm breath in the nape of the neck but found no one when it turned, terrified. And the thing goes like this with doors that open alone, phone calls from empty offices...\n\n
        Finally, it is also famous the history of several employees who celebrated a meeting and discovered a figure spying them from the door of the room where they were. When one stepped out of the room and chased in the shadow to the theater\'s \'comb\' (the area of hooks high above the stage where hangings and other gadgets hang) he noticed something invisible creeping up his shoulders until, frightened, he managed to get out and run. Since then, in the access to this part of the scene hangs a sign that warns the visitor: Watch out, it is haunting.</string>
    <string name="information_teatro">You can have a 3€ tour guide at 12:00 on Tuesdays</string>

    <string name="historia_ana">In front of the over-haunted El Español Theater is the crowded Santa Ana Square, home of the ancient cemetery of Fuencarral (we must never forget the mortuary past of these enchanted places). In this location, throughout the nineteenth century, there were several \'sightings\' of a well dressed ghost wearing period costume and a sword at the waist that even got to have talks with some of the most courageous passers-by. In any case, the stories surrounding this personage were disappearing until, in 1928, it took place, the tragedy of the Novedades Theater.\n\n
        It happened that a fire was declared during one of the performances and the fall of one of the spectators, who fled in droves, caused many others to follow him on his way to the ground and most of them end up dying crushed, when not asphyxiated by the smoke or devoured by the flames, not being able to escape. At the end of this deadly night the fire claimed the lives of eighty people... to which multiple witnesses would later see parade between screams and wailing as a procession that once again led the ghost of the Santa Ana Square.</string>

    <string name="historia_cabeza">Surely those who like the story of Les Miserables of Victor Hugo will find the story (with many traces of truth) that gives rise to the name of this singular street very familiar. A good-hearted clergyman (Don Braulio) sympathizes with a hardworking beggar (Cristóbal) whom he shelters, nourishes, and employs as his private butler until pushed by greed and following the (bad) advice of a prostitute to which he used to frequent and of whom he was hopelessly in love, he decides to assassinate his benefactor to make his fortune. \n\n
        Thus it would be that one night Cristóbal would nail a dagger into the heart of the good cleric and then cut his head with the same instrument. Legends tell us at this point that at the moment the killer dropped the cleric\'s corpse he heard a grave voice that came from nowhere and that said: \"Oh, you who are crazy and you live so bad life, soul that you are in sin, never forget that you will die! \" Be that as it may, the villain fled from the crime scene and (supposedly) hid in Lisbon until the waters calmed down, at which point he returned to the capital turned into a wealthy Portuguese landowner.\n\n
        With his new identity as a disguise and a strong detachment from the rest of the mortals as a shield, Cristóbal lived quietly for some time until one day he went to buy a ram\'s head to the Rastro (former home of the slaughterhouse and named after the blood trail left in the place) to cook it in his home. Holding it under his cloak to protect it from the eyes of the rest of the citizens, he caught the attention of a guard, who saw blood drops from his cloak from time to time. Going to show the agent the head he had bought, Cristóbal watched in horror as, in his place, he held the one of Don Braulio.\n\n
        As a result of this, Crsitóbal would confess the crime that tormented him and would be condemned to die by hanging. Since then, the street in which this macabre event took place is named after the part of the body that betrayed the murderer.</string>
    <string name="information_cabeza">Lavapies district</string>

    <string name="historia_palacio">In another point of our tour we talk about the bad idea of building on the abandoned remains of a hospital. Well, the same teaching can be extracted from that times when someone has had the idea to reuse the abandoned enclosures of an old prison. Especially when that institution has not enjoyed the best of reputations.\n\n
        The actual Ministry of Foreign Affairs was, until 1629, the old jail of the Villa, a dark well in which the prisoners were enclosed without distinguishing the committed crime, without hygienic measures and with the firm intention to forget them. The construction of the Palace, by order of Felipe IV, did not imply a great change in its use or in the conditions in which its unruly tenants were lodged, and as early as 1834 an epidemic of cholera was attacked with special intensity by the enclosure The point of being finally closed.\n\n
        As a result of its closure, and until today, ghostly lights have been reported from the building (when it was still abandoned) and mournful figures wandering through the windows, as well as heart-rending screams and inexplicable blows that, from inside the building, Have disturbed the dream of the neighbors of the area.</string>
    <string name="information_palacio" translatable="false">Plaza de la Provincia, 1. Estación de Metro próxima: Sol y Tirso de Molina</string>

    <string name="historia_mayor">If we talked about prisoners in the Palace of Santa Cruz. In the Plaza de la Villa we refer to the next natural step of many of them. This central square, which is almost as old as the city and which for much of the sixteenth century served as a market, has not been spared the truculent events.\n\n
        Not in vain, the Plaza Mayor has been the victim of three large fires. The first two, in the seventeenth century, took the lives of some neighbors and ended up with some of its buildings (of wood at that time). But the most violent would come at the end of the eighteenth and would be about to completely destroy the square. But if the dead in the fires seem to us a small thing, the matter becomes complicated when we learn that the square was the scene of the most varied public executions (vile club, gallows, bonfire ...) for the amusement of the people of Madrid. Along with all this was not missing the legends of appearings in the middle of the square, burnt smell, ghosts on the way to the scaffold ...\n\n
        Today, the city\'s hectic nightlife seems to have frightened away spirits, but rumors of strange appearances and events continue to circulate in the homes surrounding such an emblematic place.</string>
    <string name="information_mayor">Build betwen 1580 and 1619.</string>
    <string name="information_america">Linares´ Palace is open to visits. Please check the timetable at House of America web page</string>
    <string name="information_ana">Enjoy cold drink in any of the square´s bars/pubs</string>
    <string name="information_ayuntamiento">You can have a great view of the surroundings from the Palace`s terrace. Please check the timetable</string>
    <string name="information_ejercito">Every month´s last Friday, there is a change of guard, that can be seen from Alcala`s street.\nTo visit the palace please send an email to palaciodebuenavista@mde.es</string>
    <string name="information_iglesia">When visiting, please respect the cult hours</string>
</resources>
